<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Bede Engineering]]></title>
  <link href="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-04T09:35:24+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://engineering.bedegaming.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bede Gaming Ltd]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How the current mobile landscape effects developers]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/2014/10/20/developers-and-the-changing-mobile-landscape/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-20T16:55:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/2014/10/20/developers-and-the-changing-mobile-landscape</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A colleague pointed me towards an interesting <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/robnyman/mobile-trends-web-native">presentation</a> that illustrates some dramatic shifts in the mobile market. I think it&rsquo;s important that mobile app developers take a close look at how this may impact apps they are working on. Here we discuss issues and possible solutions to the problems that may arise.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The mobile OS battle</h2>

<p>Whether this can be classed as a battle anymore is up for debate but currently Android leads the way and now owns approximately 85% of the market, compare that to 2012 when it was hitting 69% and in 2011 it was only 36%! Looking across at iOS which has dropped from 18% to 11% in the same time period it is certainly looking like the two big players are still the main targets for users, Blackberry has virtually disappeared and Windows Phone seems more appealing to developers than consumers.</p>

<p>Another interesting point is the disappearance of the &ldquo;Other&rdquo; OS&rsquo;s. In 2011 this figure occupied 30% of the market, it now comprises a tiny 0.7%. My opinion here is that this is mainly to do with some of the big mobile handset manufactors moving away from Symbian as their primary platform. Samsung and Sony Ericsson have of course moved to Android whereas Nokia have adopted the Windows Phone OS. So what does this mean for developers?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/images/smartphone-os-market-share.png" title="Smartphone OS Market Share" alt="Smartphone OS Market Share"></p>

<p><em>Source: <a href="http://www.idc.com/prodserv/smartphone-os-market-share.jsp">idc.com</a></em></p>

<h3>Android fragmentation</h3>

<p>Firstly, the fragmentation of the Android market means there are many devices to support whereas on iOS there are a known set of devices to target. This leads to problems with differing device performance levels, screen resolutions and OS versions. For mobile web apps or sites you can add the usual cross browsers incompatibilities to that list.</p>

<h3>High end devices</h3>

<p>Despite Android&rsquo;s 85% market share dwarfing iOS&rsquo;s 11%, you may be surprised to hear that iOS still holds the greater market share when it comes to the high end devices. This is a key consideration to take into account when you analyse the target audience for your app or wesbite.</p>

<h3>App distribution</h3>

<p>Each OS comes with its own app distribution channel, on iOS we have the App Store and Android the Play Store (we should also try not to forget about the Windows Store). The different stores have their own restrictions on the types of app they host, the Play Store for example does not allow gambling apps and also a varying review process. The native language used to develop apps for each OS also varies:</p>

<ul>
<li>Android - Java</li>
<li>iOS - Objective-C / Swift</li>
<li>Windows - C++ / .NET</li>
</ul>


<p>This sets an obvious challenge to developers looking to publish on each store, is it really worth writing an app 3 times?</p>

<h2>So what can we do about it?</h2>

<p>Ok, I&rsquo;ve listed some of the issues that can arise when thinking about developing your latest app or website now how do we solve these isssues? Lets take a look at dealing with the many different devices on the market today. For me, the key here is to know your target audience and plenty of research. Its also useful to consider what your app or site is going to do, ask yourself these questions:</p>

<ol>
<li>What does my app do?</li>
<li>Will it need good hardware?</li>
<li>Am I willing compromise app experience?</li>
</ol>


<p>Three questions that sound obvious but once answered, can really help narrow down that extensive device list - if your app doesnt include rich graphics or intensive animations then its probably safe to widen the range of handsets you are going to target or if it&rsquo;s a game for example then you probably want to stick with the higher end of the market. Likewise if your app is heavily reliant on rich animations and graphics and a reduced experience is not really an option then again this will limit you to the high end devices.</p>

<h3>Development approach</h3>

<p>So we&rsquo;ve limited our device range but we still have a problem in that we need to build the same app 3 times in a different language to reach the maximum number of people. Or do we? No of course not - there are lots of tools available now that allow developers to write once, run anywhere (and no I dont mean Java!). In fact the aforementioned document talks about how almost half of mobile app developers choose to write apps using something other than the native language.</p>

<h4>Unity3D</h4>

<p>Unity is a hugely popular game development tool, it allows its users to create games for a wide variety of platforms. Its performance is a near match for its native equivilents and the quality of games rendering is second to none.</p>

<p>Skills for Unity tend be more difficult to find when compared to native iOS/Android and HTML5, probably because its popularity mainly stems from the games industry, however there is a large community behind it and a new Unity Store where developers can download assets and plugins for their games.</p>

<p>In my opinion, aside from the skill shortage, where Unity falls down is when it comes to app distruption. As with most channels you still have the review process for the various app stores and each new version must go through a similar review.</p>

<h4>Haxe</h4>

<p>Haxe is a relatively new tool that has been brought to my attention recently, it is source to source complier or <em>transpiler</em> for a more appropriate term. This gives developers the ability to write their app once in the Haxe language and &lsquo;transpile&rsquo; into a variety of native languages, current language support includes:</p>

<ul>
<li>iOS</li>
<li>Android</li>
<li>HTML5</li>
<li>Flash</li>
<li>C#</li>
<li>PHP</li>
<li>C++ and more</li>
</ul>


<p>The toolkit has gained backing from some well known companies like Tivo, Prezi and Zynga to name a few and also has a growing open source community which should mean further advances in the native API&rsquo;s. Where this struggles in my opinion is there will always be issues for transpiled languages where some areas of the API dont work cross platform so you maybe forced to restrict functionality in your app to cater for this. That said I imagine the API&rsquo;s available will cater for the majority of apps.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not usually a fan of transpilers, I&rsquo;ll stop now before I start a rant about CoffeeScript (one for another post!), but this on certainly looks to have its place in the market and I will be looking into this more in the near future.</p>

<h4>HTML5 and beyond!</h4>

<p>At Bede we are big adovcates of HTML5 and its surrounding technologies. Our games clients make use of the latest HTML5 API&rsquo;s, Javascript frameworks and CSS3 and our CMS uses a variant of responsive design to cater for varying screen resolutions and devices.</p>

<p>All the major mobile platforms support apps built in HTML5. Whether its an app to be published on the app store built with something like <a href="http://cordova.apache.org/">Apache Cordova</a> or one of its distributions, <a href="http://phonegap.com/">PhoneGap</a> is one of the more popular names or a web app saved from the web - Google and Apple are definitely getting behind the HTML5 revolution! An article over at <a href="http://www.sencha.com/blog/apple-shows-love-for-html5-with-ios-8">Sencha</a> details how iOS 8 adds support for many more HTML5 features, couple this with the recent addition of the &lsquo;Nitro&rsquo; Javascript engine to UIWebView and you can see how Apple are embracing HTML5.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/images/ios-html5-support.png" title="iOS HTML5 feature support comparison" alt="iOS HTML5 feature support comparison"></p>

<p><em>Source: <a href="http://caniuse.com">caniuse.com</a></em></p>

<p>Google continue to improve the Android experience by making Chrome the default browser in the latest versions of Android, finally ridding HTML5 developers of the native Android browser (or &lsquo;the IE6 of mobile&rsquo; as I like to call it). Performance used to be the main drawback of this approach but the latest developments with full webGL support meaning  hardware accerlation for HTML5 canvas and more powerful devices hitting the market, this is less of a concern these days.</p>

<p>In my opinion HTML5 is succeeding in becoming <em>the</em> write once, run everywhere choice for mobile app development. Maybe only the ultra high performance games have the performance concern now - for the vast majority of developers we can safely rely on HTML5 to deliver what we need in terms of app development. If done correctly the performance difference should be barely noticeable.</p>

<p>An added bonus is that creating a hybrid app with HTML5 means you can auto update you app without needing to go through a review in the app stores for the new content, deploying the latest version to the web will in turn update the app content. This may seem like a small advantage at first but for an app that may require frequent improvements and many iterations it is an invaluable feature.</p>

<p>As described above HTML5 plays a big part in the products delivered by Bede and based on some figures I was shown recently that indicated 40% of traffic on a popular client site came from mobile devices, I believe we are a good case study on the benefits the technology can bring. Aside from the aesthetics of sites and the rich interfaces we can create using the stack, topics like team structure and recruitment strategy are also key bonus points. Across the different teams in Bede a lot of shared code can be utilised - a repository of less mixins is available to developers and our games clients are written using our Javascript framework. Traditionally HTML5 skills have been easier to recruit for than traditional tech skills associated with mobile development, this has allowed Bede to quickly grow a highly talented team.</p>

<p>The main advantage HTML5 gives Bede over its competitors is the ability to rapidly produce rich applications that are highly configurable to the point where it is difficult to identify the software running underneath, compare 2 of our Bingo clients with 2 from a competitor and you will see what I mean!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Who is your Brent?]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/2014/10/16/who-is-your-brent/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-16T18:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/2014/10/16/who-is-your-brent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the book <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Phoenix-Project-DevOps-Helping-Business-ebook/dp/B00AZRBLHO/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1413480244&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=the+phoenix+project">The Phoenix Project</a> one of the primary foils of the &ldquo;hero&rdquo; is a guy named Brent. Brent is critical to successful work. Production incident? Call Brent. Complex database query? Brent&rsquo;s your guy. Tracing down network packet drops? Brent is already on it.  On the face of it, he is what every ops team wants twenty of, but as the book shows it is easy to become so critically dependent on one person that they become a bottleneck for the organisation. Also, Brent has several bad habits. He drops everything he&rsquo;s doing to sort out what ever is being screamed about loudest, regardless of its actual priority. He&rsquo;s also a knowledge silo - because Brent built half the complex systems in the business, he knows <!-- more -->how to solve tricky problems with them all, but all the knowledge is in his head, to the point where most of the rest of the team won&rsquo;t touch those areas. Why would they? Brent can solve the issue in a tenth of the time, and more safely.</p>

<h2>Removing the Bottleneck</h2>

<p>Much of the middle of the book is about how a mentor gets our hero thinking about how to remove that bottleneck. They tried hiring expensive experienced ops people. That failed because they still didn&rsquo;t have the knowledge of Brent, or if they gained it, it was also only in their heads. Part of the solution is to ensure that Brent is literally not allowed to touch the keyboard in production incidents, rather he must explain to a junior staff member how to step through the problems, and document the steps taken, and how to deal with the issue in future. The second part is ensuring visibility of all the work that Brent actually does, not just the stuff that was planned for him. This is one of the other key themes of the book - planned work vs unplanned work.</p>

<h2>Unplanned Work</h2>

<p>Unplanned work is a killer. Production incidents, sneaky off-the-books &ldquo;can you just get something working for me&rdquo; projects from senior management bypassing the project management / prioritisation functions, fixing another persons work because it&rsquo;s been &ldquo;done wrong&rdquo;. Not only does it not appear on your projections of how well you are doing, but it also involves parking what you should be doing, called <em>context switching</em>, or leaving <em>work in progress</em> (WIP). Gaining visibility of all the unplanned work Brent was doing was key to reducing that unplanned work. Sometimes this was even achieved by yelling at very senior management who were demanding that they &ldquo;wanted Brent to look at the issue because he&rsquo;s the best&rdquo;, despite the fact that others were already doing that piece of work.</p>

<p>As Brent&rsquo;s unplanned work went down, it became possible to leverage his actual skillset in high value operations - such as early design review and planning. Without the fire-fighting he is able to take part in processes that reduce the amount of fire-fighting! A virtuous cycle indeed.</p>

<h2>A Person is not a workstation</h2>

<p>In a twist in the later part of the book, the mysterious mentor points out to the hero, via manufacturing analogies, that a Brent is not a work centre or work station. That is, on on the macro level, a person is not a bottleneck, the function that they are carrying out is. In manufacturing you slow down your production of new work items to the speed where they can all be consumed by the next stage without queueing. One of these stations will be the slowest. That is your limiting factor or your bottleneck. (Note - a bottleneck does not specifically mean &ldquo;bad&rdquo;. No matter how optimal your process gets <em>something</em> will be the slowest part).</p>

<h2>Software Development Workstations</h2>

<p>In the software development world, your &ldquo;work stations&rdquo; are things like requirements gathering, planning, architecture and design, implementation, code review, QA testing, deployment to an environment (including production or testing environments). Where is your limiting factor? What stage holds you up the most. One of the great messages in the book is (paraphrased)</p>

<blockquote><p>Any improvements to a process that is not your bottleneck is a fake improvement</p></blockquote>

<p>Basically - because WIP is so bad, anything that does not stop WIP building up at one cost centre is not really reducing the overall turnaround time for work from inception to successful production. You should <em>only</em> focus on improving the bottleneck. When that is no longer the bottleneck, look to the next one.</p>

<h2>Identifying your Bottleneck</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s actually quite easy to do. Draw a diagram with a box for each process you have from requirements through to in production (generally a straight flow diagram). For each, identify whether they generally have a queue of items from the previous step. Now go from right to left until you find the first item that has a queue. That is your bottle neck.</p>

<p><strong>Example</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>The average queue of stories in the backlog awaiting development work is about 15 items. The average number of stories awaiting QA is 5. The &ldquo;quick&rdquo; answer is to say that clearly the biggest problem is in development - they are coping least well! But think what would happen if you improved that part of the process. QA already has a queue of work - it would only get bigger. There is no point in resolving how much work development can process until QA is no longer the bottleneck.</p></blockquote>

<p>As a real world reminder - here is an recent example from our own boards. You can see that we are building up a bottleneck on QA process. We&rsquo;ve already gone through reviewing the underlying causes. We&rsquo;re tackling this area before re-assessing our next bottleneck.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/images/QA-bottleneck-example.png" width="500" height="750" title="image" alt="images"></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Where is your bottleneck? Who is your Brent? Find them and improve them first, because all other improvements are irrelevant!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Dev-ops 80-20 Rule For Selecting A Database]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/2014/10/16/the-dev-ops-80-20-rule-for-selecting-a-database/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-16T15:23:57+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/2014/10/16/the-dev-ops-80-20-rule-for-selecting-a-database</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You&rsquo;re probably already familiar with the 80-20 rule, less catchily known as the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle">pareto principle</a> - the idea that you spend about 20% of the time it takes to complete a project building out the first 80% of the features, with the remaining 80% of the duration to complete the elusive final 20%.  There are countless applications of this idea - kind of like when you’ve just learnt a new word, examples start to crop up everywhere.  The most recent example I’ve come across describes the amount of time spent working with persistence technologies from the point of view of developers and operations.  But first some background.
 <!-- more -->
In the days of working on back office software, if there wasn’t a strong opinion already about how to solve a problem, developers were free to pick tools that met their basic checklist - will it work in production? Will the project cover the costs if they exist? And most importantly, HOW SHINY IS IT?</p>

<p>I’m as guilty as the next developer of having picked tools to work with based primarily on how much I wanted to play with them.  Being an easy tool to code with use generally made my life as a developer easier, but it was also an easy sell to management - if it takes me, the expensive developer, less time to build a solution with, it must be good for the project.  Of course, over time, lots of counter examples have cropped up: just throw “rails performance bottleneck” or “entity framework SQL fail” into google and read to learn what happens when developer magic sauce is spread liberally and allowed to determine the architecture.</p>

<p>A single instance of Bede&rsquo;s wallet can generate in the region of 10Gb data / day. It turns out that when you need to keep everything, and the product is growing daily, managing an additional 10Gb of data every day can be moderately painful.  Painful to the extent that we have an operations team, one of whose key roles is essentially to keep everything running.  Over the last year or so we’ve scaled vertically, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2147483647">run out of 32-bit integers</a>, added lots of database nodes, added data centres and strategised about archiving operational data.</p>

<p>Turns out I had fallen victim to the most common of easy vs simple fails.  In architecting the original product, we focussed on tools with which we were familiar - those that were close at hand; and therefore easy for the developer to use.  In this case MySql.  Now, MySql is extremely capable of scaling to massive data volumes, it’s currently powering numerous huge databases like Google Adwords and Facebook <a href="http://thenextweb.com/dd/2014/03/27/facebook-google-linkedin-twitter-launch-webscalesql-custom-version-mysql-massive-databases/">albeit in a much customised form</a>.  But scaling traditional RDBMs does come with a significant ops overhead.  For Bede&rsquo;s wallet, the data architecture at the code level is now pretty mature, we almost never add new data fields.  But as a business, we spend a lot of time working with the data at the persistence level - just to keep the lights on and the replicas fresh.</p>

<p>On reflection, it seems that we chose a persistence technology ignorant of the devops 80-20 rule.  I’d estimate that to date, of all the many, many man-months of time Bede&rsquo;s IT department has spent building and maintaining this product on MySql, about 20% of that time (if not less) was spent by developers building the original product, during which we benefitted from the wealth of developer tools and documentation at our disposal - it was easy to do.  At least 80% of the time, and therefore cost, has been spent by the operations team, keeping things going.</p>

<p>With my <a href="http://www.infoq.com/presentations/Simple-Made-Easy-QCon-London-2012">Simple made Easy</a> hat on, and my 20/20 hindsight goggles engaged, it was short-sighted to select the easy, comfortable technology, the one that we had experience with, without understanding how the total cost of ownership (TCO) for the decision would be contained mostly in maintenance down the line, rather than the comparatively minimal initial build.</p>

<p>So what else can we do? I think the main learning point has been to select technology with a stronger consideration for TCO.  A less smooth developer experience may well be preferable to more complex operational maintenance strategy. The persistence marketplace these days is awash with distributed database solutions with significantly improved cluster management and auto-healing capabilities, offering different types of storage and varying levels of consistency.  Some of them <a href="https://foundationdb.com/">even support ACID</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Bede Engineering]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/2014/10/15/introducing-engineering-dot-bedegaming-dot-com/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T18:13:05+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/2014/10/15/introducing-engineering-dot-bedegaming-dot-com</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A long time in the hoping, not so long in the making (thanks to <a href="octopress.org">Octopress</a> and <a href="https://github.com/wallace/justin-kelly-theme">Justin Kelly&rsquo;s Theme</a>), we&rsquo;re pretty excited to finally be able to show you our new engineering microsite.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve got some great posts lined up: everything from write ups on how we manage our army of servers to our approach to continuous delivery. In the meantime, you can browse some of our open source software using the links on the right.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
